

RESEARCH SCIENTIST · RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSIC

Department of Physics, 1110 West Green Street, Urbana, Illinois, 61801-3003, US

□ (+217) 819-9458 | ☑ ruizm@illinois.edu | 💣 miltonruizm.github.io

### **Summary** \_

Research Scientist in the Department of Physics at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign studying compact binary mergers in magnetized environments, including binary black holes in gaseous disks, black hole–neutron star, neutron star binaries, and exotic objects such as ergostars. The goal of my research is to predict and correlate observable gravitational-waves and electromagnetic signatures from these events. Also, strongly interested in alternative theories of gravity and mathematical aspects of numerical relativity. I have been supported by grants from the National Science Foundation (NSF) and the National Aeronautics and Space Agency (NASA).

## Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Research Scientist Urbana, Illinois

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS,

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

Aug 2016-

Postdoctoral Research Associate Urbana, Illinois

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS,

UIUC 2013 - 2016

CPAN Postdoctoral Research Associate

Palma de Mallorca, Spain

SPANISH NATIONAL CENTER FOR PARTICLE, ASTROPARTICLE AND NUCLEAR PHYSICS,

Universitat de les Illes Balears 2011 - 2013

Postdoctoral Research Associate Jena, Germany

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT,

Friedrich-Schiller-Universität 2009 - 2010

### **Education**

Ph.D. Physics Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL AUTONOMOUS UNIVERSITY OF MEXICO (UNAM)

Dissertation: Axial symmetry, Gravitational Waves and Boundary Conditions

Advisor: Miguel Alcubierre

Field: Gravitation; Numerical Relativity

Master of Science (Physics)

Mexico City, Mexico

UNAM June, 2006

Bachelor of Science (Physics)

Bogota, Colombia

NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

June, 2003

• Dissertation: Exact Solutions of the Einstein's Equations

# **Major Collaborations**

#### LISA Consortium:

Numerical Relativity & Analytical Relativity –Waveform modeling for MBHBs group

Urbana, Illinois

July 2018 –

April, 2009

### **Honors & Awards**

2015-2016 Fellowship for Basic Research, Colombian Ministry of Education

2011-2013 Fellowship for advance research, Spanish National Center for Astroparticle and Nuclear Physics

2005-2009 Fellowship for PhD studies, Mexican Ministry of Education

2000-2004 Fellowship for B.S. studies, Colombian Ministry of Education

Bogota, Colombia Madrid, Spain Mexico City, Mexico Bogota, Colombia

## Research Stays \_\_\_\_\_

#### Friedrich-Schiller-Universität

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT

Louisiana State University

CENTER FOR COMPUTATIONAL AND TECHNOLOGY

Jena, Germany
June-July 2008

Louisiana IIS

June - Aug 2006

# Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

**Guest Lecturer** 

INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER

• Lecture: Advanced Topics in General Relativity

Graduate level

Bucaramanga, Colombia, 2015

#### **Teaching Assistant**

Theoretisch-Physikalisches Institut, Friedrich-Schiller-Universität

• Lecture: Numerische Relativitaetstheorie (Numerical Relativity)

Undergraduate level

Jena, Germany, 2010

#### **Teaching Assistant**

THEORETISCH-PHYSIKALISCHES INSTITUT, FRIEDRICH-SCHILLER-UNIVERSITÄT

• Lecture: Allgemeine Relativitaetstheorie (General Relativity)

Undergraduate level

Jena, Germany, 2009

#### **Teaching Assistant/Grader**

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

· Lecture: General Relativity

Undergraduate level

Mexico City, Mexico, 2006-2007

#### **Teaching Assistant/Grader**

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

• Lecture: Classical Mechanics

Graduate level

Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

#### **Teaching Assistant/Grader**

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, UNAM

• Lecture: Quantum Mechanics

Graduate level

Mexico City, Mexico, 2005

# **Student Advising**

2016-2018 Abid Khan, graduate student, UIUC

2015 - **Lunan Sun, graduate student**, UIUC

2018 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Guangkuo Liu, Minh Nguyen, Kyle Nelli, UIUC

2019 - Illinois Relativity Group REU Team: Samuel Qunell, Michael Mudd, UIUC

Urbana, Illinois

Urbana, Illinois

Urbana, Illinois

Urbana, Illinois

## **Seminar and Conference Organizer**

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar

WEEKLY SEMINAR

Urbana, Illinois Jan 2017 - Dec 2017

First Symposium of Relativistic Astrophysics Bucaramanga, Colombia

INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER

June 10-12, 2015

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Seminar Urbana. Illinois

WEEKLY SEMINAR

Aug 2013 - May 2014

Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Journal Club

Urbana, Illinois

WEEKIV SEMINIAD 2013-2015

**Grants/Allocations** 

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Awarded: 487.000 node-hours

2020-2021

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity Awarded: 4,291,380 SBUs

CO-PI, HIGH-END COMPUTING RESOURCES NASA (\$2057)

2018-2021

Studies in Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

CO-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Awarded: 3,404,828.0 SUs

"Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General

**Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale** 

Awarded: 750,000 node-hours (\$ 465,500 USD)

2018-2019

2019-2020

**Black Hole Formation on Cosmological Space-times** 

PI, INDUSTRIAL UNIVERSITY OF SANTANDER/COLCIENCIAS

Awarded: \$ 16,500 USD

2014-2015

**Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers** 

CO-PI, BLUE WATERS ALLOCATION (ILL JOH)

Co-PI, Blue Waters Allocation (ILL Joh)

Awarded: 500,000 node-hours

2017-2018

Studies In Theoretical Astrophysics and General Relativity

CO-PI, RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (MCA99S008)

Awarded: 3,000,000 SUs (\$145,539.34 USD)

2017-2018

Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General **Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale** 

Co-PI, Blue Waters Allocation (ILL Joh)

Awarded: 990,000 node-hours

2016-2017

**Compact Object Binary Mergers: Simulations in Full General Relativity** 

CO-PI, XSEDE RESOURCE ALLOCATION SYSTEM (PHY100053)

Awarded 4,069,156 SUs (\$145,539.34 USD)

2014-2015

**Gravitational and Electromagnetic Signatures of Compact Binary Mergers: General Relativistic Simulations at the Petascale** 

Co-PI, Blue Waters Allocation (ILL Joh)

Awarded: 610,000 node-hours

2013-2014

**Electromagnetic Signatures of Neutron Star Binaries** 

PI, MARE NOSTRUM BSC ALLOCATION (FI-2011-3-0017)

Awarded: 120,000 core-hours (18,895.45 €)

2011-2012

## Peer Reviewer/Referee

- · Classical and Quantum Gravity
- Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society
- Physical Review D
- Physical Review Letters
- · The Astrophysical Journal

## **Invited Talks/Panelist**

Full GR simulations of stellar compact mergers: From GW170817 to GW190814

Online seminar at Certer for Astrophysics and Gravitation (CENTRA)

Lisbon, Portugal March 4, 2021

Stellar compact mergers as progenitors of gravitational waves & short-gamma ray bursts

Online seminar at Mathematics and Physics Department of Aveiro University

Aveiro, Portugal

Dec 9, 2020

Black hole-neutron star and binary neutrons star mergers: Progenitors of sGRBs

TCAN ON BINARY NEUTRON STAR WORKSHOP

Rocher institute of technology, Rochester, NY, US

July 7-10, 2020

**Community Astrophysics Science with the Einstein Toolkit Code** 

University of Guadalajara

Guadalajara, Mx Nov 20-24, 2017

Multimessenger astronomy: The new era of gravitational waves and electromagnetic

Signatures

COLLABORATIVE CONFERENCE ON GRAVITATIONAL WAVES

Jeju, Korea

May 22-26, 2017

Gravitational Waves, a New Observational Window on the Universe

PHYSICS COLLOQUIUM, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col May 16-19, 2016

Numerical relativity at the University of Santander

CELEBRATING ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF THE GENERAL RELATIVITY

Barranquilla, Col

Nov 4-6, 2015

**Numerical Solutions of the Einstein's field Equations** 

FIRST SYMPOSIUM ON RELATIVISTIC ASTROPHYSICS

Bucaramanga, Col

June 10-12, 2015

The Cactus code and Numerical Relativity

NATIONAL ASTRONOMICAL OBSERVATORY, NATIONAL UNIVERSITY OF COLOMBIA

Bogotá, Col

Dec 16-20, 2006

### Contributed Talks \_\_\_\_\_

Black hole-neutron star and binary neutrons star mergers: Progenitors of sGRBs

30TH ANNUAL MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

University of Notre Dame, IN, US

Oct 21-23, 2020

Oct 4-5, 2019

Spinning binary neutron star mergers: Effects of the spin on jet outflows

29TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Allendale, Michigan, US

Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching

APS APRIL MEETING

Denver, Colorado, US

April 13-16, 2019

GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Maximum Mass

28TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING

Wisconsin-Milwaukee, US

Oct 12-13, 2018

Accretion Disks Around Supermassive Binary Black Holes: GRMHD Simulations of Chicago, Il, US **Postdecoupling and Merger** 12TH INTERNATIONAL LISA SYMPOSIUM July 8-13, 2018 GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Columbus, Ohio, US **Maximum Mass** APS APRIL MEETING April 14-17, 2018 GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets Ann Arbor, Michigan, US 27TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING Oct 12-14, 2017 Binary neutron star mergers as engines of short gamma-ray bursts: delayed vs. prompt Washington, DC, US collapse APS APRIL MEETING Jan 28-31, 2017 MHD simulations of NSNS mergers in full GR: the role of the initial B field on the Salt Lake City, Utah, US emergence of sGRB jets APS APRIL MEETING April 16-19, 2016 Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges Evanston, II, US 25TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING Oct 1-3, 2015 **Numerical Relativity: From Vacuum to Matter Spacetimes** Bogotá-Bucaramanga, Col THE 1ST COLOMBIA-ICRANET JULIO GARAVITO ARMERO MEETING Nov 23-27, 2015 Black Hole-Neutron Star Coalescence as engines that power sGRBs Bogotá, Col SECOND WORKSHOP ON ASTRONOMY July 27-31, 2015 Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges II Baltimore, Maryland, US APS APRIL MEETING April 11-14, 2015 Gravitational Waves as Probes of Dark Matter Spikes around Massive Black Holes Urbana, Il, US THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR Sep 3, 2014 General relativistic corrections to the pulsar spin-down luminosity Savannah, Georgia APS APRIL MEETING April 5-8, 2014 I-Love-Q Relations in Neutron Stars and their Applications to Astrophysics, Gravitational Urbana, Il, US **Waves and Fundamental Physics** THEORETICAL ASTROPHYSICS AND GENERAL RELATIVITY SEMINAR Feb 2, 2014 Initial boundary value problem of the Z4c formulation of General Relativity Evanston, II, US 23TH MIDWEST RELATIVITY MEETING Oct 25-26, 2013 The Initial Value Problem in General Relativity Palma de Mallorca, Spain CoCoNuT MEETING Nov 26-28, 2012 High Order Outer Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation Oppurg, Germany WORKSHOP ON NUMERICAL AND MATHEMATICAL RELATIVITY Oct 11-13, 2012

Barcelona, Spain

Feb 15-17, 2012

Magnetospheres of compact objects in Force-Free Plasma

2ND IBERIAN GRAVITATIONAL WAVE MEETING

May 20-22, 2011

#### Constraint Preserving Boundary Conditions for the Z4c Formulation of General Relativity

19TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON GENERAL RELATIVITY AND GRAVITATION

Mexico City, Mx

Oct 25-27, 2010

## **Refereed Publications**

Minidisk Dynamics in Accreting, Spinning Black Hole Binaries: Simulations in Full General Relativity

V. PASCHALIDIS, J. BRIGHT, M. Ruiz, R. GOLD

Submitted to Astrophys. J. Lett. ArXiv:2102.06712

2021

Multimessenger Binary Mergers Containing Neutron Stars: Gravitational Waves, Jets, and  $\gamma$ -Ray Bursts. Invited review for the Research Topic: Neutron Star Physics in the Multi-Messenger Discourse.

M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, A. Tsokaros

Frontiers Astronomy and Space Science (in press) ArXiv:2102.03366

202

Gravitational Waves from Disks Around Spinning Black Holes: Simulations in Full General Relativity

E. Wessel, V. Paschalidis, A. Tsokaros, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro

Phys. Rev. D 103, 043013

Phys. Rev. D 102, 124077

Black hole-neutron star coalescence: effects of the neutron star spin on jet launching and dynamical ejecta mass

M. Ruiz, V. Paschalidis, A. Tsokaros, S. L. Shapiro

Magnetic Ergostars, Jet Formation and Gamma-Ray Bursts: Ergoregions versus Horizons

M. Ruiz, A. Tsokaros, S. L. Shapiro, Kyle Nelli, Sam Quell

Phys. Rev. D 102, 104022

2020

2020

GW190814: Spin and equation of state of a neutron star companion

A. Tsokaros, **M. Ruiz**, S. L. Shapiro

Astrophys. J. 905, 48

Ergostar models: where do they reside?

A. Tsokaros, **M. Ruiz**, S. L. Shapiro

Phys. Rev. D 101, 064069

**Prospects for Fundamental Physics with LISA** 

E. BARAUSSE ET AL.

Gen. Rel. Grav. 52, 81

Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations of Binary Neutron Star Mergers in General Relativity: Effects of Magnetic Field Orientation on Jet Launching

 ${\bf M.~Ruiz}$ , A. Tsokaros, S. L. Shapiro

Phys. Rev. D 101, 064042

2020

The great impostors: Extremely compact, merging binary neutron stars in the mass gap posing as binary black holes

A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, L. Sun, S. L. Shapiro, K. Uryu

Phys. Rev. Lett. 124, 071101

2019

2019

Dynamically stable ergostars exist: General relativistic models and simulations

Enabling real-time multi-messenger astrophysics discoveries with deep learning

A. Tsokaros, **M. Ruiz**, L. Sun, S. L. Shapiro, K. Uryu

Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, 231103

Nature Reviews Physics 1, 600

E. HUERTA ET AL.

Phys.Rev. D100, 024061

Effect of spin on the inspiral of binary neutron stars

A. TSOKAROS, M. Ruiz, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, K. URYU

20:

FEBRUARY 26, 2021 MILTON RUIZ · CURRICULUM

Are fast radio bursts the most likely electromagnetic counterpart of neutron star mergers resulting in prompt collapse?  V. PASCHALIDIS, M. Ruiz	Phys. Rev. D100, 043001
Effects of spin on magnetized binary neutron star mergers and jet launching M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, V. PASCHALIDIS, S. L. SHAPIRO, K. URYU	Phys.Rev. D99, 084032 2019
Magnetic Braking and Damping of Differential Rotation in Massive Stars L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys.Rev. D99, 064057 2019
Constant circulation sequences of binary neutron stars and their spin characterization A. Tsokaros, K. Uryu, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys. Rev. D98, 124019 2018
Jet launching from binary black hole-neutron star mergers: Dependence on black hole spin, binary mass ratio and magnetic field orientation  M. Ruiz, A. TSOKAROS, S. L. SHAPIRO	Phys. Rev. D98, 123017
Simulating the Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Incorporating Gas Pressure Perturbations and Different Rotation Profiles  L. Sun, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys. Rev. D98, 103008 2018
Disks Around Merging Binary Black Holes: From GW150914 to Supermassive Black Holes A. Khan, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys. Rev. D97, 044036 2018
GW170817, General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Simulations, and the Neutron Star Maximum Mass M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, A. Tsokaros	Phys. Rev. D 97, 021501R 2018
The initial boundary value problem for free-evolution formulations of General Relativity D. Hilditch, M. Ruiz	Class. Quan. Grav. 35 015006 2018
GRMHD simulations of prompt-collapse neutron star mergers: the absence of jets M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys. Rev. D 96, 084063 2017
Magnetorotational Collapse of Supermassive Stars: Black Hole Formation, Gravitational Waves and Jets L. Sun, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Phys. Rev. D 96, 043006
Gravitational wave content and stability of uniformly, rotating, triaxial neutron stars in general relativity T. Tsokaros, M. Ruiz, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro, L. Baiotti, K. Uryu	Phys. Rev. D 95, 124057 2017
Binary neutron star mergers: a jet engine for short gamma-ray bursts M. Ruiz, R. Lang, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro	Astrophys. J. Lett. 824, L6 2016
Relativistic simulations of black hole-neutron star coalescence: the jet emerges V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro	Astrophys. J. Lett. 806, L14 2015
Accretion disks around binary black holes of unequal mass: GRMHD simulations of postdecoupling and merger R. Gold, V. Paschalidis, M. Ruiz, S. L. Shapiro, Z. B. Etienne, H. Pfeiffer	Phys. Rev. D 90, 104030 2014

The Pulsar spin-down luminosity: simulations in general relativity

M. Ruiz, V. Paschalidis, S. L. Shapiro

Phys. Rev. D 89, 084045

2014

Almost-Killing conserved currents: a general mass function

M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, C. Bona.

Phys. Rev. D 89, 025011

Induced scalarization in boson stars and scalar gravitational radiation

M. Ruiz, J. C. Degollado, M. Alcubierre, D. Nunez, M. Salgado

Phys. Rev. D 86, 104044

The role of the ergosphere in the Blandford-Znajek process

M. Ruiz, C. Palenzuela, F. Galeazzi, C. Bona.

Mon. Not. R. Aston. Soc. 423

Constraint preserving boundary conditions for the Z4c formulation of general relativity

M. Ruiz, D. HILDITCH, S. BERNUZZI

Phys. Rev. D 83, 024025

Dynamic transition to spontaneous scalarization in boson stars

M. Alcubierre J. C. Degollado, D. Nunez, **M. Ruiz**, M. Salgado

Phys. Rev. D 81, 124018

Multipole expansions for energy and momenta carried by gravitational waves

M. Ruiz, M. Alcubierre, D. Nunez, R. Takahashi

Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 2467

2008

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric evolution codes in numerical relativity

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

Gen. Rel. Grav. 40, 159 2008

Outer boundary conditions for Einstein's field equations in harmonic coordinates

M. Ruiz, O. RINNE, O. SARBACH

Class. Ouant. Grav. 24, 6349

2007

2010

### **Conference Publications**

Gravity and Light: Combining Gravitational Wave and Electromagnetic Observations in the 2020s

R. FOLEY ET AL.

FFRMII AR-PUR-19-169-AF

2019

Deep Learning for Multi-Messenger Astrophysics: A Gateway for Discovery in the Big Data

Era

arXiv:1902 00522

G. ALLEN ET AL. 2019

Regularization of spherical and axisymmetric codes in numerical relativity

M. Ruiz, M. ALCUBIERRE, D. NUNEZ

Rev. Mex. Fis. 53, 144

8

## **Computer Skills**

Operating Systems: UNIX, Linux, Windows, Mac OS X

Programming Language: FORTRAN, C, C++

Graphics and Image Processing: Mathematica, Microcal Origin, SM, Gnuplot, VIsIt, Python

Document Preparation LaTeX, Microsoft Office, Open/Libre Office

Other: Bash scripting, Basic system administration



### **Spanish (native speaker)**

**English** 

# Primary References \_\_\_\_\_

### **Professor Miguel Alcubierre**

Departamento de Gravitación y Teoría de Campos Instituto de Ciencias Nucleares UNAM Mexico City, Mexico malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx +55 562-33-371 Ext. 3371

### **Professor Vasileios Paschalidis**

Astronomy and Physics Departments University of Arizona Tucson, Arizona, US vpaschal@email.arizona.edu +1 520-621-9643

### **Professor Stuart L. Shapiro**

Department of Physics University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Urbana, Il, US slshapir@illinois.edu +1 217-333-5427